# GRIGORIY OVCHINNIKOV

# NLP Data Scientist | ML Engineer

Georgia, Tbilisi

ogoje@protonmail.com in grigoriy-o-a679501b5/

NLP Data Scientist and ML Engineer with 4 years of applying natural language processing for business problem solving. Strong knowledge of deep learning foundations, classical and advanced ML algorithms. Proficiency in working with ML frameworks and databases for business problem-solving.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Python, SQL

Natural Language Processing: PyTorch, transformers, gensim, nltkt

Machine learning: PyTorch, Scikit-learn, XGBoost, LightGBM, NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Plotly, MLflow

Databases: PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Cassandra, HBase

Version Control & Deploy & Infrastructure: Git, GitLab CI/CD, Docker(compose, swarm), Flask

GCP: Cloud Functions, Cloud Run, Cloud Storage, PubSub, VertexAI

Web scraping: Scrapy, Puppeteer, lxml

Project management: Jira, Confluence, Trello

Other: EDA, Data cleaning, Visualization, Modelling, Propensity Modelling, Model interpretation, Natural

Language Processing, Statistics, Experimental design, Hypothesis testing, MVP

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Platforma November 2020 - Present

NLP Data Scientist | ML Engineer

Moscow, Russia

- Built a NLP based feedback handling solution (modelling, knowledge distillation, deployment) based on pretrained Roberta model, with applying knowledge distillation according to transformer distillation conception(TinyBERT).
- Suggested and implemented an NLP-inspired(item2vec) approach for website representation learning based on clickstream data, giving several advantages over the previous approach.
- Implemented state-of-the-art methods for a look-alike modeling task with positive unlabeled (PU) learning using PySpark and PyTorch with a significant uplift in offline and online metrics.
- Pipeline stack: Python, Transformers, gensim, PyTorch, TorchServe, Hadoop, Pyspark

S7 TechLab October 2018 - October 2020

Junior Data Scientist

Moscow, Russia

- Conducted research and data analysis to address predictive maintenance task. Provided estimates of remaining useful life through supervised machine learning in the big data department.
- Developed ML models for improving accuracy of decision support system using cluster analysis and supervised multiclass classification.
- Scraping external data with Python, Building MVP with R Shiny, Python Flask-restx.
- Pipeline stack: Python, Airflow, PySpark, S3, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Cassandra, Kafka.

#### SIDE PROJECTS

CatchBlogger 7 | Co-founder and developer of YouTube influence marketing platform.

06 2022

- Responsible for whole data management pipeline: extraction, transformation and loading.
- Pipeline stack: Python, Puppeteer, GCP: Cloud Functions, Cloud Scheduler, Cloud Storage

#### **EDUCATION**

National Research Nuclear University (MEPhI)

Master's degree in Applied Mathematics and Informatics(incomplete)

**September 2018 – June 2020** 

Moscow, Russia

Volgograd State Technical University (VSTU)

Bachelor's degree in Informatics and Computer Engineering

**September 2014 – June 2018** 

Volgograd, Russia

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

- Google Cloud, Big Data and Machine Learning Fundamentals [November 2022]
- TensorFlow on Google Cloud [November 2022]
- Drawing conclusions from data, MIPT, Yandex [October 2020]

## Languages

- English B2(Upper intermediate)
- Russian Native